<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Section xmlns="urn:com.io7m.structural:8:0"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         id="352ba8b4-1d9d-443c-929a-21027c374207"
         title="Plan Language">

  <Subsection title="Overview">
    <Paragraph>
      The <Term type="term">plan</Term> language is a domain-specific language used to write
      <Link target="7b6d8296-cba1-448b-96e0-10e89b61bec0">plans</Link>.
    </Paragraph>
    <Paragraph>
      A <Term type="term">plan</Term> program consists of immutable
      <Link target="ee2248ae-b120-40ba-8ad7-96c82750d1b2">variables</Link>,
      <Link target="cbc2e395-4351-49fb-b90e-eb38d21e454c">tasks</Link>, and
      <Link target="f6a513dc-e704-4e62-a562-b2530d9f5e67">barriers</Link>.
    </Paragraph>
  </Subsection>

  <Subsection title="Tasks"
              id="cbc2e395-4351-49fb-b90e-eb38d21e454c">
    <Subsection title="Description">
      <Paragraph>
        A <Term type="term">task</Term> is an executable element that, when evaluated, causes a
        <Link target="c9234354-ea97-4693-826c-a3ccd9a006d7">tool execution</Link>
        to be executed on an appropriate <Link target="935b5ed1-1fbb-4d8b-9930-c5a3e79c7afd">agent</Link>.
      </Paragraph>
    </Subsection>
    <Subsection title="Agent Constraints"
                id="8aadf34b-61e3-4780-b98f-6ff638ec2786">
      <Paragraph>
        An <Term type="term">agent constraint</Term> is an expression used to reduce the set of
        <Link target="43fa1060-d9b5-4e79-b139-015e1d6591f3">agents</Link>
        that will be considered to be candidates for executing a given task. A constraint expression is evaluated
        against the set of
        <Link target="3f9341dd-4d51-42e8-b0f5-370591e58afa">labels</Link>
        on a given agent. A constraint expression is a value of the given inductive type:
      </Paragraph>
      <FormalItem title="Agent Expression">
        <Verbatim>
          <xi:include href="agent-match-exp.txt"
                      parse="text"/>
        </Verbatim>
      </FormalItem>
      <Paragraph>
        Whether an expression matches a given agent <Term type="expression">a</Term> is given by the following inductive
        proposition:
      </Paragraph>
      <FormalItem title="Agent Expression Matches">
        <Verbatim>
          <xi:include href="agent-match-exp-prop.txt"
                      parse="text"/>
        </Verbatim>
      </FormalItem>
      <FormalItem title="Agent Expression Matches Explanation">
        <ListUnordered>
          <Item>
            An expression <Term type="expression">AMAnything</Term> matches any agent.
          </Item>
          <Item>
            An expression <Term type="expression">(AMIsSubsetOf xs)</Term> matches an agent
            <Term type="expression">a</Term>
            where each label
            <Term type="expression">x</Term>
            in
            <Term type="expression">xs</Term>
            is in
            <Term type="expression">(agentLabels a)</Term>.
          </Item>
          <Item>
            An expression <Term type="expression">(AMIsSupersetOf xs)</Term> matches an agent
            <Term type="expression">a</Term>
            where each label
            <Term type="expression">x</Term>
            in
            <Term type="expression">(agentLabels a)</Term>
            is in
            <Term type="expression">xs</Term>.
          </Item>
          <Item>
            An expression <Term type="expression">(AMIsOverlapping xs)</Term> matches an agent
            <Term type="expression">a</Term>
            where there exists at least one label
            <Term type="expression">x</Term>
            in
            <Term type="expression">xs</Term>
            that is in
            <Term type="expression">(agentLabels a)</Term>.
          </Item>
          <Item>
            An expression <Term type="expression">(AMIsEqualTo xs)</Term> matches an agent
            <Term type="expression">a</Term>
            where
            <Term type="expression">xs = (agentLabels a)</Term>.
          </Item>
          <Item>
            An expression <Term type="expression">(AMIsNotEqualTo xs)</Term> matches an agent
            <Term type="expression">a</Term>
            where
            <Term type="expression">xs ≠ (agentLabels a)</Term>.
          </Item>
        </ListUnordered>
      </FormalItem>
      <Paragraph>
        Formal descriptions of the semantics of these expressions are given in the
        associated <Link target="efaa5ba5-bc57-5284-bfdb-4c03bc73db04">proof script</Link>.
      </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>
        A given task is associated with a mandatory <Term type="term">requirement</Term> expression, and an optional
        <Term type="term">preference</Term>
        expression. When a
        <Term type="term">plan</Term>
        program needs to find an agent for a given task, only the agents matching the
        <Term type="term">requirement</Term>
        expression will be considered as candidates. When multiple agents match, any agent that happens to match the
        <Term type="term">preference</Term>
        expression will be more likely to be offered the task first.
      </Paragraph>
    </Subsection>
  </Subsection>

  <Subsection title="Barriers"
              id="f6a513dc-e704-4e62-a562-b2530d9f5e67">
    <Subsection title="Description">
      <Paragraph>
        A <Term type="term">barrier</Term> is an executable element that is conceptually a kind of no-op
        <Link target="cbc2e395-4351-49fb-b90e-eb38d21e454c">task</Link>
        that does not require an agent, and that immediately
        <Link target="31edd30e-6e55-4284-a81a-9060e109f82c">succeeds</Link>
        as soon as its dependencies have succeeded.
      </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>
        Barriers are essentially a convenient object used to control the execution of plan. A barrier
        <Term type="expression">b</Term>
        can be specified with a set of dependencies, and the execution of any plan elements that depend on
        <Term type="expression">b</Term>
        will not proceed until all the dependencies of <Term type="expression">b</Term> have completed successfully.
      </Paragraph>
    </Subsection>
  </Subsection>

  <Subsection title="Agents"
              id="43fa1060-d9b5-4e79-b139-015e1d6591f3">
    <Subsection title="Description">
      <Paragraph>
        A <Term type="term">agent</Term>, from the perspective of the <Term type="term">plan</Term> language, is an
        abstract object that can accept
        <Link target="cbc2e395-4351-49fb-b90e-eb38d21e454c">tasks</Link>
        for execution. In reality, agents are the objects that reside in
        <Link target="935b5ed1-1fbb-4d8b-9930-c5a3e79c7afd">agent hosts</Link>.
      </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>
        An <Term type="term">agent</Term> adheres to the following finite state machine, with all agents starting in the
        <Term type="expression">ASIdle</Term>
        state:
      </Paragraph>
      <FormalItem title="FSM">
        <Image source="agentState.png"
               width="602"
               height="482">Agent state
        </Image>
      </FormalItem>
      <Paragraph>
        When an agent is not executing a task, it is in the <Term type="expression">ASIdle</Term> state. The system may
        select the agent as a candidate for executing a given task. If the agent accepts the task for execution, it
        proceeds to the <Term type="expression">ASAccepted</Term> state and then, after an indefinite period
        <LinkFootnote target="29a01202-ba65-478c-9761-d5c335816991"/>, proceeds to the
        <Term type="expression">ASExecuting</Term>
        state. The task on the agent then either succeeds or fails, causing transitions to the
        <Term type="expression">ASSucceeded</Term>
        or
        <Term type="expression">ASFailed</Term>
        states, respectively. The agent then transitions back to the
        <Term type="expression">ASIdle</Term>
        state.
      </Paragraph>
    </Subsection>
  </Subsection>

  <Subsection title="Variables"
              id="ee2248ae-b120-40ba-8ad7-96c82750d1b2">
    <Paragraph>
      Variables...
    </Paragraph>
  </Subsection>

  <Subsection title="Tool References"
              id="4f5e9536-bac1-4fd9-8549-5c2404be1d3d">
    <Paragraph>
      Tool References...
    </Paragraph>
  </Subsection>

  <Subsection title="Syntax"
              id="79a5df3a-a787-49b4-9839-29f5f4411547">
    <Subsection title="Overview">
      <Paragraph>
        Programs in the <Term type="term">plan</Term> language are specified in a strictly-defined XML format
        conforming to a published <Link target="c69b56e6-ba24-44a3-8be3-de12b24275c5">XSD schema</Link>.
      </Paragraph>
    </Subsection>

    <Subsection title="Example">
      <Paragraph>
        The following trivial example program defines two
        <Link target="cbc2e395-4351-49fb-b90e-eb38d21e454c">tasks</Link>,
        <Term type="expression">com.io7m.task0</Term>
        and
        <Term type="expression">com.io7m.task1</Term>. The
        <Term type="expression">com.io7m.task1</Term>
        task is specified to depend on
        <Term type="expression">com.io7m.task0</Term>, and an
        <Link target="8aadf34b-61e3-4780-b98f-6ff638ec2786">agent constraint</Link>
        is used to ensure that
        <Term type="expression">com.io7m.task1</Term>
        executes on the same <Link target="43fa1060-d9b5-4e79-b139-015e1d6591f3">agent</Link> as the
        <Term type="expression">com.io7m.task0</Term>.
      </Paragraph>

      <FormalItem title="Example">
        <Verbatim>
          <xi:include href="example-plan.xml"
                      parse="text"/>
        </Verbatim>
      </FormalItem>
    </Subsection>
  </Subsection>

  <Subsection title="Semantics"
              id="fb2213d8-136e-4901-977b-ac7fcd5c929c">
    <Subsection title="Overview">
      <Paragraph>
        The <Term type="term">plan</Term> language is a concurrent, non-deterministic language specified as a series of
        <Link target="d312770c-c3c0-4092-85ec-8e2dbf4b082f">state transitions</Link>. Evaluation of a program in the
        <Term type="term">plan</Term>
        language effectively proceeds by non-deterministically choosing an element from the set of elements in the
        program and attempting to make that element transition to a new state. Each
        <Term type="term">state transition</Term>
        has an associated set of
        <Term type="term">preconditions</Term>
        that indicate whether an element can move to a new state according to that state transition; if the
        preconditions for that state transition evaluate to
        <Term type="expression">true</Term>, the element transitions to the new state.
      </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>
        For the set of known state transitions,
        <Link target="823194b3-8ff0-46dd-adf1-8bc722535fcb">formal proofs</Link>
        exist that have verified the following properties of the language rules:
      </Paragraph>
      <FormalItem title="Verified Properties">
        <ListUnordered>
          <Item>
            The preconditions for each defined state transition are
            <Term type="term">decidable</Term>. That is, it is always possible to determine if a state transition is
            applicable to a given element. Accordingly, it is always possible to determine if an element exists to which
            any state transition applies.
          </Item>
          <Item>
            The state transitions, as defined, have the property of
            <Term type="term">strong progress</Term>. That is, if the program is not in a state
            considered <Link target="12444ab8-7abd-4bc4-a2f9-4288f2c657dd">completed</Link>, then there is always a
            state transition that will apply to allow the program to take another step of execution.
          </Item>
          <Item>
            The state transitions, as defined, will always preserve various invariants such as "
            <Link target="f6a513dc-e704-4e62-a562-b2530d9f5e67">barrier</Link>
            elements are never considered for execution on an agent", "an element with no dependencies can never be
            waiting for dependencies", and etc.
          </Item>
        </ListUnordered>
      </FormalItem>
      <Paragraph>
        It follows that programs in the <Term type="term">plan</Term> language will always terminate in a finite number
        of steps (due to configurable bounds on the times elements are allowed to remain in various states), although
        the proofs do not currently attempt to verify this.
      </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>
        The actual <Term type="term">implementation</Term> of the plan evaluation logic in the server has
        <Term type="term">not</Term>
        been formally verified; the proofs only indicate that the design appears to be sound, not that the
        implementation is bug-free.
      </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>
        The evaluation of a <Term type="term">plan</Term> language program should be considered to operate in the
        presence of a set of <Link target="43fa1060-d9b5-4e79-b139-015e1d6591f3">agents</Link>, with the state of each
        agent being subject to change at any time. Many state transitions are dependent on an appropriate agent being
        available to execute parts of the plan.
      </Paragraph>
    </Subsection>
    <Subsection title="States"
                id="d312770c-c3c0-4092-85ec-8e2dbf4b082f">
      <FormalItem title="States">
        <Image source="exec.png"
               width="640"
               height="482">States
        </Image>
      </FormalItem>
      <Paragraph>
        Each element in the plan has a defined initial state:
      </Paragraph>
      <FormalItem title="Initial States">
        <ListUnordered>
          <Item>
            If an element has a non-empty set of
            <Link target="9147dd3d-3f83-424b-aa3b-1f826f47a4f3">dependencies</Link>, then the element starts in the
            <Term type="constant">EWaitingForDependencies</Term>
            state.
          </Item>
          <Item>
            If an element has an empty set of
            <Link target="9147dd3d-3f83-424b-aa3b-1f826f47a4f3">dependencies</Link>, then the element starts in the
            <Term type="constant">EReady</Term>
            state.
          </Item>
        </ListUnordered>
      </FormalItem>
      <Paragraph id="31edd30e-6e55-4284-a81a-9060e109f82c">
        An element is considered to have <Term type="term">succeeded</Term> if it has reached the
        <Term type="constant">ESuccess</Term>
        state. An element is considered to have
        <Term type="term">failed</Term>
        if it has reached either of the <Term type="constant">EFailure</Term> or
        <Term type="constant">EFailureTimedOut</Term>
        states.
      </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>
        If an element has a non-empty set of dependencies, then it remains in the
        <Term type="constant">EWaitingForDependencies</Term>
        state until either all of its dependencies have <Term type="term">succeeded</Term>, or at least one of its
        dependencies has
        <Term type="term">failed</Term>. If any of an element's dependencies have failed, then the element itself
        transitions immediately to the <Term type="constant">EFailure</Term> state. If all the element's dependencies
        have <Term type="term">succeeded</Term>, the element transitions to the
        <Term type="constant">EReady</Term>
        state.
      </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>
        If an element is in the <Term type="constant">EReady</Term> state, then the element immediately transitions to a
        new state dependent on its type. If the element is a
        <Link target="f6a513dc-e704-4e62-a562-b2530d9f5e67">barrier</Link>, then the element immediately transitions to
        the <Term type="constant">ESuccess</Term> state. Otherwise, if the element is
        a <Link target="cbc2e395-4351-49fb-b90e-eb38d21e454c">task</Link>, the element immediately transitions to the
        <Term type="constant">EWaitingForAgent</Term>
        state.
      </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>
        If an element is in the <Term type="constant">EWaitingForAgent</Term> state (which implies that it must be
        a <Link target="cbc2e395-4351-49fb-b90e-eb38d21e454c">task</Link>), it will wait for an
        <Link target="43fa1060-d9b5-4e79-b139-015e1d6591f3">agent</Link>
        to become available to execute the task. The maximum amount of time that the element will wait is determined by
        a configurable bound of <Term type="expression">t</Term> seconds; if no agent has become available after
        <Term type="expression">t</Term>
        has elapsed, the element transitions to the
        <Term type="constant">EFailureTimedOut</Term>
        state. Otherwise, if an agent becomes available and accepts the task for execution, the element transitions to
        the
        <Term type="constant">EExecuting</Term>
        state.
      </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>
        Once an element is in the <Term type="constant">EExecuting</Term> state, the element will wait for the executing
        agent to report success or failure. The maximum amount of time that the element will wait is determined by a
        configurable bound of <Term type="expression">t</Term> seconds; if the agent has not reported success or failure
        after <Term type="expression">t</Term> has elapsed, the element transitions to the
        <Term type="constant">EFailureTimedOut</Term>
        state. If the agent reports success, the element transitions to the
        <Term type="constant">ESuccess</Term>
        state. If the agent reports failure, the element transitions to the
        <Term type="constant">EFailure</Term>
        state.
      </Paragraph>
    </Subsection>
    <Subsection title="Completion"
                id="12444ab8-7abd-4bc4-a2f9-4288f2c657dd">
      <Paragraph>
        A given program <Term type="expression">p</Term> has
        <Term type="term">completed</Term>
        if any of the following conditions hold:
      </Paragraph>
      <FormalItem title="Completion Conditions">
        <ListUnordered>
          <Item>
            For each element <Term type="expression">e</Term> in <Term type="expression">p</Term>, the state of
            <Term type="expression">e</Term>
            is
            <Term type="constant">ESuccess</Term>.
          </Item>
          <Item>
            There is an element <Term type="expression">e</Term> that exists in
            <Term type="expression">p</Term>
            such that the state of <Term type="expression">e</Term> is
            <Term type="constant">EFailure</Term>
            or <Term type="constant">EFailureTimedOut</Term>.
          </Item>
        </ListUnordered>
      </FormalItem>
      <Paragraph>
        A program in a <Term type="term">completed</Term> state no longer takes any steps of evaluation.
      </Paragraph>
    </Subsection>
    <Subsection title="Dependencies"
                id="9147dd3d-3f83-424b-aa3b-1f826f47a4f3">
      <Paragraph>
        The elements in a <Term type="term">plan</Term> program form a <Term type="term">directed acyclic graph</Term>.
        A given element <Term type="term">e</Term> has a possibly-empty set of
        <Term type="term">dependencies</Term>
        that must have <Link target="31edd30e-6e55-4284-a81a-9060e109f82c">succeeded</Link> before
        <Term type="term">e</Term>
        can be processed.
      </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>
        Dependencies are the only means by which to control the order of execution of elements within a
        <Term type="term">plan</Term>
        program; in a program where none of the elements have dependencies, implementations are free to execute any
        number of elements concurrently and in any order.
      </Paragraph>
    </Subsection>
  </Subsection>

  <Footnote id="29a01202-ba65-478c-9761-d5c335816991">
    Typically, real implementations of agents will start executing tasks immediately. Agent implementations should avoid
    using long queues to store tasks; agents should favour rejecting tasks that cannot be started promptly over placing
    the tasks into queues. The reasoning behind this is that agents should assume that they are part of a large set of
    distributed agents, and that if they cannot execute a given task immediately, they can likely assume that another
    agent will be available in the set to execute the task if they cannot. In a system where agents immediately tried to
    monopolize all tasks, many other agents would be left sitting idle with no tasks to execute.
  </Footnote>

</Section>
